It's said that to be a poet
هناك مقولة : إذا أردت أن تكون شاعراً
you have to go to hell and back.
يجب عليك أن تزور الجحيم وتعود.
The first time I visited the prison,
عندما زرت السجن لأول مرة،
I was not surprised by the noise of the padlocks,
لم يفاجئني صرير الأقفال،
or the closing doors, or the cell bars,
ولا الأبواب المغلقة ولا قضبان الزنزانة،
or by any of the things I had imagined.
ولا أي من تلك الأشياء التي تخيلتها مسبقاً.
Maybe because the prison is in a quite open space.
يمكن أن يكون السبب إن السجن في فضاء هادئ مفتوح.
You can see the sky.
حيث يمكن رؤية السماء.
Seagulls fly overhead, and you feel like you're next to the sea,
والنوارس تطير فوق وتشعر بأنك قريب من البحر،
that you're really close to the beach.
وأنك قريب فعلا من الشاطئ.
But in fact, the gulls are looking for food in the dump near the prison.
وفي الواقع النوارس تبحث عن الطعام في تلك القمامة القريبه من السجن.
I went farther inside and I suddenly saw inmates moving across the corridors.
ذهبت للداخل أكثر فرأيت السجناء يتحركون في الممرات.
Then it was as if I stepped back and thought
ثم بدا لي كما لو إنني رجعت وفكرت
that I could have very well been one of them.
بأنني كان يمكن أن أكون واحده منهم.
If I had another story, another context, different luck.
لو كانت لي قصة، وحالة أخرى ،وحظاً مختلفاً.
Because nobody - nobody - can choose where they're born.
لأن لا أحد، لا أحد يمكن أن يختار أين يولد.
In 2009, I was invited to join a project
دعيت في 2009 للمشاركة في مشروع
that San Martín National University conducted at the Unit 48 penitentiary,
تقوم به جامعة سان مارتن الوطنية في وحدة السجن 48،
to coordinate a writing workshop.
لتنسيق ورشة عمل للكتابة.
The prison service ceded some land at the end of the prison,
خصصت إدارة السجن قطعة أرض في نهاية السجن.
which is where they constructed the University Center building.
حيث قاموا ببناء بناية مركز الجامعة.
The first time I met with the prisoners,
وعند لقائي الأول بالسجناء،
I asked them why they were asking for a writing workshop
سألتهم لماذا يريدون ورشة للكتابة
and they told me they wanted to put on paper
أخبروني بأنهم يريدون أن يضعوا على الورق
all that they couldn't say and do.
كل ما لا يستطيعون قوله أو فعله.
Right then I decided that I wanted poetry to enter the prison.
حينها قررت أن الشعر يجب أن يدخل إلى السجن.
So I said to them why don't we work with poetry,
فقلت لهم: لم لا نتعامل بالشعر،
if they knew what poetry was.
إذا كانوا يعرفون ما هو الشعر.
But nobody had a clue what poetry really was.
ولكن لم يكن لأي منهم أي فكرة عن ما هو الشعر.
They also suggested to me
ثم أقترحوا علي
that the workshop should be not just for the inmates
بأن لا تكون الورشة فقط للسجناء
taking university classes, but for all the inmates.
الذين يدرسون بالجامعة بل لكل السجناء.
And so I said that to start this workshop,
وقلت لهم لكي نبدأ هذه الورشة،
I needed to find a tool that we all had in common.
أحتاج أولاً إلى أداة مشتركة لدينا جميعاً.
That tool was language.
كانت هذه الأداة هي اللغة.
We had language, we had the workshop. We could have poetry.
لدينا اللغة ولدينا الورشة فيمكننا الحصول على الشعر.
But what I hadn't considered was that inequality exists in prison, too.
ولكن ما لم أحسب حسابه أن الفوارق توجد في السجن أيضاً.
Many of the prisoners hadn't even completed grammar school.
كثير من السجناء لم يكملوا مدارس اللغة.
Many couldn't use cursive, could barely print.
كثير منهم لا يعرف كتابة الكلمات أو الحروف،
They didn't write fluently, either.
ولم يكونوا قادرين على الكتابة بطلاقة.
So we started looking for short poems.
لذلك بدأنا بالبحث عن أشعار قصيرة.
Very short, but very powerful.
قصيرة جداً ولكن ذات معني.
And we started to read, and we'd read one author, then another author,
وبدأنا القراءة وقرأنا لكاتب ثم لكاتب آخر،
and by reading such short poems, they all began to realize
وبعد قراءتنا هذه الأشعار القصيرة، بدأوا يميزون،
that what the poetic language did was to break a certain logic,
بأن لغة الأشعار تكسر منطقاً معيناً،
and create another system.
لتنشئ بذلك نظام آخر.
Breaking the logic of language also breaks the logic of the system
إنها تحطم منطق اللغة وتحطم كذلك منطق النظام
So a new system appeared,
وبذلك ظهر نظام جديد،
new rules that made them understand very quickly,
و قواعد جديدة جعلتهم يفهمون بصورة أسرع،
- very quickly -
و أسرع كثيراً،
that with poetic language
وذلك بلغة الشعر
they would be able to say absolutely whatever they wanted.
أصبحوا قادرين على قول ما يريدون تماماً.
It's said that to be a poet you have to go to hell and back.
يقال كي تكون شاعراً يجب أن تزور الجحيم و تعود.
And they have plenty of hell. Plenty of hell.
وكان لديهم الكثير من الجحيم. الكثير من الجحيم.
One of them once said: "In prison you never sleep.
قال أحدهم: "في السجن لا تنام أبداً
You can never sleep in jail. You can never close your eyelids."
لا يمكنك النوم في السجن، لا يمكنك إغلاق جفونك"
And so, like I’m doing now, I gave them a moment of silence,
وكما أفعل الآن، أعطيتهم دقيقة صمت،
then said, “That's what poetry is, you guys.
ثم قلت: "هذا هو الشعر يا أصدقاء
It's in this prison universe that you have all around you.
إنه في عالم السجن هذا المحيط بكم.
Everything you say about how you never sleep,
كل ما تقولونه عن عدم إمكانكم النوم،
it exudes fear.
فإنه يفرز الخوف.
All the things that go unwritten -- all of that is poetry."
وكل ما لا يمكن كتابته، ذلك هو الشعر"
So we started appropriating that hell;
ثم أخذنا نبحث في ذلك الجحيم،
we plunged ourselves, headfirst, into the seventh circle.
ثم غصنا بأنفسنا و رؤوسنا في الطبقة السابعة.
And in that seventh circle of hell, our very own, beloved circle,
وفي الطبقة السابعة من الحجيم، طبقتنا الخاصة و المحبوبة جداً،
they learned that they could make the walls invisible,
تعلموا كيف يمكنهم جعل الجدران غير ظاهرة،
that they could make the windows yell,
ثم أمكنهم جعل النوافذ تصرخ،
and that we could hide inside the shadows.
وكيف يمكن أن نختفي داخل الظلال،
When the first year of the workshop had ended,
وعندما انتهت أول سنة من الورشة،
we organized a little closing party,
نظمنا حفلة ختامية صغيرة،
like you do when a job is done with so much love,
كما تفعلون عندما تنجزون عملا مع الكثير من الحب،
and you want to celebrate with a party.
وتريد الاحتفال بإقامة حفلة لذلك.
We called family, friends, the university authorities.
دعونا العوائل والأصدقاء وإدارة الجامعة.
The only thing the inmates had to do was read a poem,
ولم يكن على السجناء إلا قراءة الشعر،
and receive their diplomas and applause.
و تسلم شهاداتهم مع التصفيق.
That was our simple party.
هذه كانت حفلتنا البسيطة.
The only thing I want to leave you with
وكل ما أريد تركه معكم
is the moment in which those men,
هي اللحظة التي كان بها هؤلاء الرجال،
some of them just huge when standing next to me,
وبعضهم كان ضخماً للغاية عندما وقفوا بجانبي،
or the young boys - so young, but with an enormous pride,
والشباب الصغار جداً ولكن بفخر عال،
held their papers and trembled like little kids and sweated,
يمسكون بأوراقهم و يرتجفون ويعرقون كالأطفال،
and read their poems with their voices completely broken.
ويقرأون أشعارهم بأصواتهم المنكسرة.
That moment made me think a lot
جعلتني هذه اللحظة أفكر كثيرا
that for most of them, it was surely the very first time
بأن ذلك كان للكثير منهم لأول مرة بالتأكيد
that someone applauded them for something they had done.
عندما يصفق لهم أحد لشيء قاموا بعمله.
In prison there are things that can't be done.
هناك في السجن أشياء لا يمكن القيام بها.
In prison, you can't dream. In prison, you can't cry.
في السجن لا يمكنك أن تحلم. وفي السجن لا يمكنك البكاء.
There are words that are virtually forbidden, like the word "time,"
وهناك كلمات ممنوعة فعلا مثل كلمة "الوقت،"
the word "future," the word "wish".
وكلمة "المستقبل" وكلمة "أتمنى".
But we dared to dream, and to dream a lot.
لكننا تمكنا من أن نحلم ونحلم كثيرا.
We decided that they were going to write a book.
لقد قررنا بأن يبدأوا بكتابة كتاب.
Not only did they write a book, but they also bound it themselves.
ولم يكتفوا بكتابة الكتاب بل صحفوه بأنفسهم.
That was at the end of 2010.
كان ذلك نهاية عام 2010.
Then, we doubled the bet and wrote another book.
ثم ضاعفنا الرهان و كتبوا كتابا ثانياً.
And we bound that one, too.
وصحفناه أيضاً.
That was a short time ago, at the end of last year.
كان ذلك قبل فترة قصيرة ، في نهاية العام الماضي.
What I see week after week,
ما أراه أسبوعابعد أسبوع،
is how they're turning into different people;
هو كيف يتحولون إلى بشر مختلفين،
how they're being transformed.
كيف يتم تحويلهم.
How words are empowering them with a dignity they had never known,
كيف أشعرتهم الكلمات بكرامة لم يحسوا بها أبدا،
that they couldn't even imagine.
ولم يمكنهم تخيلها أيضاً.
They had no idea such dignity could come from them.
ولم تكن لديهم أي فكرة بأن مثل هذا السمو يصدر عنهم.
At the workshop, in that beloved hell we share, we all give something.
في الورشة وفي جحيمنا المحبوب تشاركنا وأعطى كل واحد شيئا.
We open our hands and hearts and give what we have, what we can.
نفتح أيدينا وقلوبنا ونعطي ما لدينا وما نستطيع.
All of us; all of us equally.
جميعنا ،وجميعنا بالتساوي.
And so you feel that at least in a small way
وبذلك تشعر بأنك على الأقل وبطريقة بسيطة
you're repairing that huge social fracture
بأنك تصلح هذا الشرخ الاجتماعي الكبير
which makes it so that for many of them,
الذي يجعل للبعض منهم،
prison is their only destination.
النهاية الوحيدة هي السجن.
I remember a verse by a tremendous poet, a great poet,
أذكر أبياتاً من شاعر عظيم و كبير،
from our Unit 48 workshop, Nicolás Dorado:
من ورشة الوحدة 48. نيكولاس دورادو:
"I will need an infinite thread to sew up this huge wound."
"أحتاج إلى خيط لا ينتهي لأخيط به هذا الجرح الكبير
Poetry does that; it sews up the wounds of exclusion.
الشعر يفعل ذلك لأنه يخيط جروح الاستبعاد.
It opens doors. Poetry works as a mirror.
إنه يفتح الأبواب .إنه كالمرآة.
It creates a mirror, which is the poem.
إنه يخلق مرآة هي الشعر.
They recognize themselves, they look at themselves in the poem
إنهم يميزون أنفسهم، وينظرون إلى نفسهم في الشعر
and write from who they are, and are from what they write.
ويكتبون من يكونون ومن أين أتت كتاباتهم.
In order to write,
لأجل أن تكتب،
they need to appropriate the moment of writing
عليهم أن يختلسوا وقت الكتابة
which is a moment of extraordinary freedom.
التي هي لحظة الحرية غير المعتادة.
They have to get into their heads, search for that bit of freedom
عليهم أن يدخلوا في رؤوسهم للبحث عن تلك الحرية
and that is also useful to realize that freedom is possible
وهذا أيضا ممكن ليعرفوا أن الحرية ممكنة
even inside a prison,
حتى داخل السجن،
and that the only bars we have in our wonderful space
وإن القضبان الوحيدة في فضائنا الرائع
is the word "bars,"
هي كلمة "القضبان،"
and that all of us in our hell burn with happiness
وبعدها يحترق كل منا في جحيمه بسعادة
when we light the wick of the word.
عندما نشعل فتيلة الكلمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I told you a lot about the prison, a lot about what I experience
حكيت لكم كثيرا عن السجن ،وكثيرا عن تجربتي
every week, and how I enjoy it and transform myself with the inmates.
كل أسبوع وكيف أستمتع بها للتحول بنفسي مع رفاقي.
But you don't know how much I'd like it
لكنكم لا تعرفون كم أحبها
if you could feel, live, experience, even for a few seconds,
إذا أمكنكم أن تشعروا و تعيشوا و تجربوا لبضعة ثوان،
what I enjoy every week and what makes me who I am.
ما أستمتع به كل أسبوع وما يجعلني أنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Martín Bustamante: The heart chews tears of time;
(مارتن بوستامانتي) :القلب يمضغ دموع الوقت،
blinded by that light,
أعماه ذلك الضوء
it hides the speed of existence
إنه يخفي سرعة الوجود
where the images go rowing by.
حيث تمر الظلال ضاربة بمجذافها.
It fights; it hangs on.
إنه يحارب،إنه يجالد.
The heart cracks under sad gazes,
وينهار القلب تحت النظرات الحزينة،
rides on storms that spread fire,
ويركب العواصف التي تنشر النار،
lifts chests lowered by shame,
ويرفع الصدور التي أدناها الخجل،
knows that it's not just reading and going on,
يعرف إنها ليست قراءات وكلمات عابرة،
it also wishes to see the infinite blue.
إنه يتمنى أن يرى الأزرق اللامتناهي.
The heart sits down to think about things,
ويجلس القلب ليفكر في الأشياء،
fights to avoid being ordinary,
و يحارب كي يتجنب المعتاد،
tries to love without hurting,
يحاول أن يحب دون أن يؤذي،
breathes the sun, giving courage to itself,
يتنفس الشمس ليعطي لنفسه الشجاعة،
surrenders, travels toward reason.
ويستسلم مسافرا نحو الأسباب.
The heart fights among the swamps,
القلب يحارب وسط المستنقعاتـ،
skirts the edge of the underworld,
ويدور حول حافات العالم السفلي،
falls exhausted, but won't give in to what's easy,
ويسقط مجهدا لكنه لا يستسلم للبسيط من الأمور،
while irregular steps of intoxication
بينما الخطوات غير الطبيعية للسموم
wake up,
تستيقظ،
wake the stillness.
توقظ السكون.
I'm Martín Bustamante,
أنا مارتن بوستامانتي
I'm a prisoner in Unit 48 of San Martín,
أنا سجين في الوحدة 48 في سان مارتن،
today is my day of temporary release.
اليوم هو يوم إطلاق سراحي الموقت.
And for me, poetry and literature have changed my life.
لثد غير الشعر والأدب حياتي.
Thank you very much!
شكرا جزيلا!
Cristina Domenech: Thank you!
كريستينا دومينيتش: شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)